Until now, we've been talking about JavaScript and
features of the langauge itself, not necessarily how we use JavaScript in HTML.
We'll start to see that in the next lesson but before we get there,
there's just one more thing to talk about which is JavaScript strings.
In any programming langauge, there's going to be some notion of strings.
Strings are usually a collection of characters and in JavaScript,
as in many other programming languages, strings are immutable.
That means we can't change them.
So in this lesson, we'll start talking about how we can use strings and
some of the different functions that the strings offer.
We can always get the number of characters in a string using the length property and
access each character by its (0-based) index using the charAt function or
array notation.
In this example, we have a name or variable called name,
which is set to toucan.
And I can get its length property which will
return 6 because there are 6 letters in the word.
I can also get individual characters out of there
using the index which is (0-based).
Here I'll get the third character, (0-based), and
that will return c, that's character, 0, 1, 2, 3.
Likewise, I can use the array notation, we can think of it as name [3],
this will also return the character c.
We'll keep coming back to this, that JavaScript strings are immutable,
that means I can't change the string.
For instance, if I have a variable called animal and I set it to cat,
and I try to set animal[0] to r, to change it to rat, and I print it,
it'll still be cat, because I can't change the characters in the string.
We can, however, use functions to return a new string that is
a modified version of the original string.
For instance, I have a string called friend, which is set to turtle,
and I can use the toUpperCase function to return a new string shown here,
which is those letters but uppercase.
However, if I print the value of friend, it's still lowercase turtle.
I can't change the characters in the variable but
I can create a new string that has those changed characters.
Another common operation is to remove white space from a string.
Here I have a string called message, which is set to hello everyone, but
you see that there is some space before the h and after the e.
I can use the trim function on the message,
that will remove the white space at the beginning and the end and
return a new string which is the old string but without the white space.
Now, I set message = message.trim,
we've lost the original string but now a message holds the new one.
I can even call the function on a string literal,
it doesn't necessarily have to be a string variable.
Here I'm calling it on the string literal, cat.
I'm concatenating it with mouse and I'm setting my animal to the concatenation
so that when I print it, my animal is catmouse.
Now, a common operation that we may want to perform is knowing whether a string
contains some other string that is knowing that one string is a substring of another.
We'll start with this string,
which reads programming in JavaScript is fun, and we want to know does that string,
does that variable, start with this string here, programming.
The startsWith function will return true,
because this string does start with those characters.
It's worth pointing out that startsWith is case sensitive, so
when I ask does it start with programming in all capital letters,
it will return false, because it does not start with those letters.
In addition to startsWith, there's endsWith.
I might want to know, does this string ends with this string?
It's okay that it includes a white space and this will return true because,
as we see here, it does end with that string.
Last, I might wanna know does this string include, for instance,
JavaScript anywhere, not necessarily at the beginning or the end.
And this will, again, return true because it does contain or
does include JavaScript.
Sometimes we might want to know where in the string we can find that substring,
startsWith, endsWith, and includes, all return booleans.
In this case,
we have a string called title which will be set to the title of my book.
And I can use the search function to ask does that string contain this string here.
Rather than returning true or false, this will return the index
of the original string where it finds this string for which it's searching.
It'll return 4 because it does contain the string title and that starts at the 0,
1, 2, 3, 4th index of the string, so it'll return 4.
However, if it does not contain that string, for
instance banana, then it will return -1 to indicate
that the string does not contain this other string that we're looking for.
So we've seen how to determine whether one string contains another string.
But what if we want to know does a string adhere to some pattern, for
instance, is it an email address, is it a string and then a character and
then a string and then a character, and so on, is it phone number,
does it adhere to some pattern of numbers and letters and special characters.
In order to do that, we need to use what are known as regular expressions.
A regular expression is just a pattern of characters.
But it's not a string but rather a specification
of the characters that we want to see whether another string matches.
We say that a string matches a regular expression if it adheres to that pattern.
For example, we might want to know does this string consist of exactly
three digits, digits being zero through nine.
123 matches but abc does not match,
12 does not match because we want to know does it contain exactly three digits.
12345 does not match for the same reason.
Let's see how we can use regular expressions within JavaScript strings.
We can pass a regular expression to a string's search function
to see if it matches the pattern.
And this will be considered a match if any part of the string
matches that regular expression.
Here, we have a string status that reads, I am working VERY hard, I can use
the status.search function to see if it contains the regular expression, VERY.
The regular expression is noted here.
Note that it is not a string.
In the previous few slides, we saw the search function with a string.
Here, VERY is a regular expression denoted by the slash here and here.
Because this string status does contain VERY
here at index 13, this will return 13.
However, when I pass the regular expression, very with lowercase,
search will return -1, indicating that this is not found because it is case
sensitive here, it doesn't match VERY, capital V, etc.
Unlike strings, if I had passed a string,
it would return -1 because it doesn't match, it's case sensitive.
However, I can, with a regular expression, tell it to ignore case by putting the i
at the end indicating that it should be case insensitive, it should ignore case.
Now it will return 13,
because ignoring case, the original string does contain that string very.
Now, a regular expression or regex is itself an object and it has functions of
its own including the function test which we'll see for the rest of this lesson.
In this case, I have a regular expression, not a string but a regular expression,
script indicated with the two slashes here.
And I'm going to invoke its test function to see if that regular expression
is included in the string that is the argument of this function.
That is, I'm going to look to see if this is included here and, of course, it is.
So it will return true.
That's great, that seems handy but we've seen all that already with strings.
So what can we do different with regular expressions
that we couldn't do with strings already?
In particular, regular expressions allow us to specify multiple valid characters
that we can consider for matching.
For instance, maybe I want to look for any of some range of specific characters.
Here I have a string called numbers, consisting of these characters here.
And now I can use this regular expression to see if it contains a 0, a 1, or a 2.
That is, I have my regular expression notation with the slashes and
then within the regular expression notation, I have the brackets.
The brackets indicate, or they say, look for any character in this range,
or in this particular case, in this set of characters.
That is, we'll look to see if the string contains a 0, a 1,
or a 2, any character in this set or in this range.
Of course, numbers, the string numbers does contain a 0, a 1, or
a 2 as we see right there.
And so this will return 4, which is the (0-based) index of the 2 right here.
Alternatively, I could specify my regular expression using
the slash notation and then the range using the bracket notation.
I can call the test function on that regular expression.
I can pass numbers, the string numbers, to the regular expression and
this will return true, because, remember, test returns true or false.
So that led us to see if the string contained a 0, a 1, or 2.
But what if I want to know if it contains any digit or, for instance,
any lowercase letter?
In this example, I have a string called password and
now rather than specifying every character for which I'm looking,
I can just specify the range using this notation, here I'm saying,
I'm looking for a match where there's any character in this range,
a-z, those are of course the lowercase letters.
The search function will return the index of the first match.
Here the first match in password is the lowercase p at index 0.
So calling search will return 0, because that's the first place we find a match
that is that contains a lowercase letter.
With these ranges, I can also use some special characters.
For instance, the \d indicates any digit being 0 through 9.
Here's we're searching for any digit and it'll return 8, which is the index
of this character here, because that's a match for \d.
Now, we'll start to see how we can combine these different ranges
to do more powerful searching or pattern matching with regular expressions.
Here I have a string called code, it's a bunch of letters and numbers and
I want to use this regular expression to find out does it contain
a digit followed by a lowercase letter followed by a digit.
So I'll use my regular expression notation using the slashes and I'll specify
that the first character in the sequence, or the regular expression, is a digit.
I could have used /d as well.
The next one has to be a lowercase letter followed by a digit.
In this case, the function will return 5.
Why?
Because, at this point, we see a match here, we see a digit followed by
a lowercase letter, which is the d, followed by a digit, which is the 4.
There are other matches as well, for instance, 4e5 but
this will return the first match which starts here at index number 5.
We can also tell it to look for characters not in a particular range.
We want to know are there characters that are not, for
instance, in a digit or a lowercase letter.
So here we have some characters and we'll use the search function, and now we'll use
the caret notation to indicate that we are not looking for these characters.
So by specifying this range, we're saying we're looking for a character that is
not in the range 0 through 9 and lowercase a through lowercase z.
And we'll get 6 because capital K is not in that range and
that's the index 6 in that string.
Regular expressions allow us to do more powerful pattern matching or
searching using what are known as quantifiers.
For instance, quantifiers can help us know whether the string contains an optional
single occurrence of some character.
Let's look at this line here.
Here we have the regular expression, we're using its test function and
then this is the string we're seeing if it matches that pattern.
We want to know does this string contain a character followed by an optional digit.
The question mark means 0 or 1.
The question mark means it's okay if it contains this character, in this case,
a digit, and it's okay if it doesn't but it can't contain more than one.
In this case, the 1 matches this, so that's a match.
It's followed by a lowercase letter, so
this will return true because it matches this pattern.
In this next example, we're going to see
does it have a lowercase letter followed by an optional number.
Again, or a digit, the digit is optional, so it's okay if there's no match here.
We continue, we find a lowercase letter which is the b and
this will return true as well.
In this final case, though, we'll look for a match of a lowercase letter.
We do see one digit but, remember, the digit in this case,
because of the question mark quantifier, can only be a single occurence.
The thing that follows it would have to be now a lowercase letter but it's not, so
this will return false.
The other quantifier is the asterisk, which means 0 or more.
The question mark meaning 0 or 1,
the asterisk means just multiple occurences but optional.
In this case, we have a lowercase letter followed by 0 or more digits.
So it will match the 1, the 2, the 3, and
then next it will match another lowercase letter, and so this will return true.
There are also special characters indicating the start of the string and
the end of the string.
Similar to what we saw with startsWith and endsWith but
now using regular expressions.
In this case, the caret means startsWith.
Remember, before we saw the caret inside the square brackets,
meaning not, here it means starts with.
So this wants to know does this string start with
a lowercase letter followed by a digit, it does, so it will return it true.
Does this one start with a lowercase letter followed by a digit?
No, this will return false.
You'll note that this particular string does
have a lowercase letter followed by a digit, for instance, b1, but
it doesn't start with that and that's why it returns false.
Here we can use the $ to indicate endsWith,
here we want know does this end with two lowercase letters, I guess
the easiest way to think about it is working at the end and working backwards.
Does it end with a lowercase letter?
Yes, is that preceded by a lowercase letter?
Yes, so this will return true.
In this case, though, does it end with a lowercase letter?
No, so it will return false.
Again, you'll note that this does, in a couple of places,
match two lowercase letters but it doesn't end with the lowercase letters.
Then this lets us detect exact matches.
I want to know does this string contain only,, for
instance, a letter followed by a number followed by a letter.
And we can combine the startsWith and endsWith and quantifiers.
So here we wanna know does this string, a1b, match this regular expression here?
Well, it's asking does it start with a lowercase letter, it does.
Followed by a digit, followed by a lowercase letter, and
ending with the lowercase letter.
Yes, so it's true, it does match that pattern.
A lowercase letter, a digit, a lowercase letter, and nothing else.
In this example, we see that it starts with the lowercase letter
followed by the digit followed by a lowercase letter.
But now, it's expecting the end of the string, we're not at the end,
we see another character, so this will return false.
And finally, we'll start with a lowercase letter and what this means,
remember, our quantifier using the asterisk optional,
any number of digits or lowercase letters that will match the 1,
that will match the b, that'll match the 2.
And here, we see it ends with the lowercase letter and that's true.
In summary, we've seen how to use JavaScript's string
functions to determine whether one string contains another string and
how to use regular expressions to do more powerful pattern matching.