Last week, we started looking at how we can create dynamic web content by
embedding JavaScript in our HTML pages.
And we saw jQuery, a library that made it easier to manipulate the DOM.
This week, we'll look at two other libraries that allow us to create dynamic
web content starting with a powerful and popular library known as React.
React is a JavaScript library for building user interfaces.
In the React model, a webpage is composed of components that have a life cycle and
change state, which affects how they're rendered.
React introduces this notion of the VirtualDOM,
which allows us to add and remove elements.
React is created and maintained by Facebook and
is used by many well known companies.
There are three important features to React.
The first is modularity.
Modularity allows us to organize the code into reusable components
that can be connected together.
This allows us to separate functionality
into compartmentalize everything that we want to do.
Second, React provides lifecycle maintenance.
This involves modifying the component based on its state,
adding event listeners and simplifying the way in which components are rendered.
And last, React introduces a technology known as JSX,
which allows us to embed HTML right into our JavaScript.
Components are the core of React.
Components make up the nodes inside the VirtualDOM and
each component includes and maintains a state that changes with events.
The components independently maintain their state and
applications can be configured to respond to the different component events.
So I mentioned this VirtualDOM a few times now, what do I mean by that?
Well remember before that the DOM is the structural
representation of all the HTML elements.
In React, the VirtualDOM selectively renders and re-renders
the different parts of the tree, or the different nodes, based on state changes.
The VirtualDOM is more efficient because it does
the least amount of DOM manipulation when it comes to updating components.
Let's look at a visual example of how the normal DOM works.
When any node in the DOM is updated, for instance some HTML element,
the browser will update or re-render all the nodes in the DOM.
So in this case I have a tree representing my DOM.
Let's say that one of these nodes changes.
In response to that, the entire DOM is re-rendered as a reflection of the change.
In the VirtualDOM, React figures out which part of the DOM needs to change,
and only changes the nodes that are affected.
This involves two steps, diff and reconciliation.
In the diff step React will to identify the node that has changed,
and in reconciliation figure out which other nodes are affected by the change.
Then it will re-render only the nodes that were affected by the change and
not re-render any of the other nodes.
As a developer there are three steps to using React.
First, within the webpage's HTML you'll need to allocate some position
where the React component will be dropped or rendered, for instance a div.
The React component is then implemented in JavaScript.
It has an initial state and
it has events that could change the component's state during its lifecycle.
And then it has a render function which will be used to draw that component or
generate its HTML.
And then last the component is dropped into the allocated
position that came from step one.
So let's look at the HTML first.
In our HTML page,
we'll create a div to represent a location where the React component will be placed.
Here's HTML, and in the head of the HTML we need to include the React JavaScript.
As with jQuery, React is not part of the web browser by default, so
we'll need to include React in the page.
Then in the body of my HTML page, we'll have some div,
which is where we'll place the React component.
Here I've labeled it with the ID container.
You can of course choose anything you want, but
I'll use container in all my examples.
And then last, we have the JavaScript code.
Note here, that for the JavaScript, we're specifying the type
of the JavaScript which is text/jsx.
Finally we'll write our JavaScript.
What is JSX?
JSX is JavaScript XML Syntax Transform, it's a way of putting
HTML right into our JavaScript and then converting it to React code.
As an example, here we see that we've specified JSX as the type of JavaScript.
This function ReactDOM.render,
is going to be used to put this HTML at this location.
Notice that we're mixing the JavaScript, which is this and
this, with HTML which is this.
JSX allows us to do that in the appropriate places.
Let's finish with a full hello world example using react.
As before, we need to make sure that we include the react JavaScript files or
libraries in the header of our HTML.
Then we'll set up a div that we'll label with the id container.
This is where we're going to insert or drop our React component.
Within the JavaScript tags, we'll use this function, React-DOM.render
that specifies the HTML that we should put at that location.
Using jsx we can embed HTML right into our JavaScript.
Here, we'll just say Hello, React!
This specifies what we want to display and the second argument to the render
function, this specifies where we're going to display it.
We'll select that element by its ID,
that will be the div that we've labelled container.
In the next few lessons, we'll dive much deeper into using React.
We'll see how we define components and
how write the functions that modify those components based on user events.
We'll see how components interact with each other.
And then finally look at real world tools that are used for
developing React applications.