This week we're talking about React, a JavaScript library for
building dynamic webpages.
Now the most important part of React is this idea of components.
Components are modular, reusable chunks of code that we can drop into our
HTML pages and that dynamically generate content based on their state and
user events In this lesson, we'll start to see how to define components and
how we can include them in our html pages.
React components are JavaScript objects
that are based off the React.Component prototype.
And in the next few slides, we'll see two different ways to create react components.
React components have four important parts, their properties,
their state variables and their callback functions or event handlers, and
then their render function, which is used to generate the HTML.
The VirtualDOM manages each component and
calls the render function whenever it's time to re-render that component.
Here we see the classical way of creating a react component.
We'll use the React.createClass function and
pass it an object which contains the component specification.
So we see that we're creating a variable called HelloComponent
which will be an object, and
we'll use this React.createClass function to create that object.
The argument to createClass is itself an object.
That one of the properties of that object is render which is a function
that will be called when it's time to draw or render this component.
The render function needs to return the HTML to be rendered,
to be drawn and here we're using JSX.
If you remember from last time,
JSX is a technology that allows us to embed HTML right in our JavaScript.
Once we've created the custom component in our JavaScript, then we can render it or
drop it into our HTML using the reactDOM.render function.
ReactDOM.render takes two arguments.
The first is the JSX or HTML that we want to render.
Here we see that we're rendering a component called hello component,
which is the one that we just created.
You can think of it as creating new HTML tags.
The second argument to rReactDOM.render is the location of where we want to drop or
place that component, and here we're using the DOM.
We created a div called container, we're selecting that element by its ID,
and we'll put the HelloComponent at that location in the HTML.
Another way of creating the react components is using
the notation from a version of JavaScript known as ES6.
We'll see ES6 a little bit later this week, but for now,
suffice it to say that the ES6 is the most recent version of JavaScript and
allows us to create a class instead of a single object.
This is the notation or
the syntax that I'll use the rest of this week when creating react components.
Rather then creating a variable called HelloComponent, we'll create a class.
This class will extend the React.Component base class.
Here we're defining the render function in our class.
Which looks the same as it did before and
will be invoked when we drop this component into the html.
At the beginning of this lesson I said there are four important parts of
a react component.
We already seen the render function and now here are the next two important parts.
The first are the component's properties, properties are the attributes and
values that are set when the component is created,
they should never be modified after initialization.
The other important part is the state, the state is also attributes and values,
but they represent the current state of the component, based on what it does or
represents.
They can and should be modified during the component's life cycle.
And in the next few slides we'll see some examples of each.
It's worth pointing out that both the properties and the state can be used when
rendering the component, but the important difference is that properties are set
when the component is initialized, and state changes during the component's life.
Let's talk about component properties.
As I mentioned, component properties are the attributes and values that
are assigned when the object is created, but should not be modified afterward.
A component can access its properties through a property called props,
which is an object containing all of the property values.
We can set the properties of a component when we render the component
using ReactDOM.render.
Here we see that we have a component called HelloUser, and
we set its name property to the string Maria.
So you can think of this as passing a variable or passing an argument to
the component when its' created but what we're doing is setting it's name property.
Now in the component I have my hello user component and
in it's render function I can return some HTML for instance hello and
then I can access the property using this.props.name.
This.props is the name of the property in the component.
It is an object and one of its properties is name which
was initialized when we rendered this component using ReactDOM.render.
The next important part of the component is its state.
The state is also a set of variables but
these can change during the component's life cycle.
The state is always initialized in the constructor,
which is the function that's called when the component or object is created.
And then it can access the state properties, using this.state.
In this example we'll show the number of times that this page has been viewed.
We create a component called TimesViewed, and it will have a constructor.
The constructor as I mentioned is the function that's called
when this component or object is created.
Now the arguments to the constructor are the props and we'll need to
pass those to the super class constructor using this notation super(props).
Demo initialize a variable called timesViewed = 0,
and then we'll look in local storage.
You may remember last week when we started talking about JavaScript in HTML,
that local storage was a way of storing values in between accesses to a webpage.
If local storage has a property called timesViewed
then we will set our local timesViewed variable to that value.
If it doesn't have a times viewed, then timesViewed will still be 0, so
that when we increment it here, we're incrementing it either to one,
if it's the first time, or incrementing whatever its previous value was.
Now here's the most important part of this example,
setting the state of this component.
We use this.state to access it's state.
And we set it to this object where we have the property numViews and
the variable timesViewed.
Last, to make sure this works for the next time we open this page,
we need to update localStorage.
Then we have the render function for times viewed.
The render function will return some text in bold and
it will return the numViews variable from the state.
That is, if we can access this component's state using this.state.
State is an object and one of its properties is numViews.
And this will return the number of views which we set here in the state, the last
part of this lesson is to talk about what's known as the component life cycle.
Each component goes through three stages of it's life where it's being created,
where it's being updated and then where it's being destroyed or
as we say unmounted.
At each point of its life cycle, React can invoke,
optionally, different functions that you can write for controlling the component.
The first part of the component's life is where it's being created, or
as we say, mounted.
We already saw the constructor,
which is the function that's called when the component is created and
initializes the state potentially based on the properties.
Then before the component is added to the VirtualDOM
the component will componentWillMount is called, in this function we can do any work that
we want to do before we add it to the VirtualDOM.
Once it's added to the VirtualDOM then the render function is called and
then after that ComponentDidMount is invoked and
at that point the component can start accessing other parts of the VirtualDOM.
Next in the components life is its cycle of being updated.
We are going to see later how the component can react to user events.
But, for now, let's talk about the four callback functions
that can be invoked during its lifecycle.
First is component will receive props.
This is invoked right before it receives new props, for instance,
when its parent is being re-rendered.
This allows us to compare the old props to the new props
in case we need to do anything.
The component doesn't have to be re-rendered.
Before it's re-rendered, the shouldComponentUpdate is called, and
that returns a boolean, indicating whether this component should be re-rendered.
If its about to be re-rendered, the componenWillUpdate is called and
then after its re-rendered, componentDidUpdate is called.
Last When it's the end of the component's life and it's about to
be removed from the VirtualDOM, the componentWillUnmount function is invoked.
In this lesson, we've seen how to create a component,
how to specify it's properties and it's state, and
how to use it's render () function to use JSX to render the HTML for that component.
In the next lesson,
we'll start looking at how the component can react to user events.